Guide to the Thomas Cripps papers, 1839-2009 and undated, bulk 1940s-2009 RL.00269
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas Cripps papers
1839-2009 and undated bulk 1940s-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cripps, Thomas
RL.00269
98 Linear Feet
Retired professor of history at Morgan State University, scholar of the history of African Americans in the motion picture industry, prolific author of books and articles on the subject, and script writer. The papers of Thomas Cripps date from 1839 to 2009, and are arranged into three divisions: films, photographic stills of African American actors and productions, and professional papers, the largest group. Taken as a whole, the films, movie stills, research files, and publication files document Cripps's investigations into representations of racial and ethnic stereotypes in popular culture, particularly in film, but also touch on other issues such as gender in popular culture, portrayal of race in Nazi Germany, and the social dimensions of African American life in the U.S. during the 20th century. Other materials stem from college-level courses taught by Cripps on these same topics, and include many of the visual resources he used in his classes. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Approximately 62,475 Items
Access Restrictions
The films and movie stills are open to use. However, the remaining series are closed to access pending processing.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies are available in the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Thomas Cripps papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003, 2011, and 2017.
Biographical Note
Thomas Cripps is a historian specializing in the portrayal of African Americans in film, and is a retired faculty member of Morgan State University. He has written five books, including Slow Fade to Black: The Negro in American Film, 1900-1942 (Oxford, 1997), as well as many articles and television scripts. In addition, Cripps has contributed to the production of several television series such as American Cinema, Hollywoodism: Jews, Movies and the American Dream, and Richard Wright: Black Boy. Cripps was awarded gold medals in international film festivals for his 1976 script, Black Shadows on a Silver Screen.
Collection Overview
The Thomas Cripps collection dates from approximately 1839 to 2009, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1940-2009, and is arranged into three main divisions: films, photographic stills of African American actors and productions, and professional papers, which is the largest group of the three (closed pending processing). The materials as a whole can be used to study a variety of themes and subjects: racial or ethnic stereotypes in popular culture (chiefly African American, but also Jewish, Irish, and Asian); American and European television culture, broadcasting, and advertising; African American artists; African American film-makers, most notably Oscar Micheaux; U.S. political and social events in the 20th century, including the Depression and the Civil Rights Movement; educational institutions for African Americans; and the teaching of African American history in U.S. higher education. There are significant research materials on Nazi Germany propaganda and the portrayal of race in the party's films.
The thirty-seven films found in the Films Series consist of film shorts, clips from feature films, newsreels, "Soundies," and television commercials, and were collected by Cripps for their portrayals of African Americans, performance by African Americans, or production by African Americans from the turn of the century into the late 1960s 1970s. He also collected filmic materials reflecting other racial and ethnic stereotypes, as seen in the Ethnic Films reel. There are viewing copies for all films.
The Still Photographs Series consists of hundreds of publicity stills and other images taken from U.S. and British feature films featuring African American actors from the silent film era through the 1970s. Many entries, which have been retained from the original envelope labels, carry titles from individual films, but other prints were arranged by Cripps into topical categories such as "Black Athletes," "Jungle Pix," "Silent Films," and "Exotic Primitives."
Cripps's professional papers, a very large group, are closed to access pending processing. They are currently loosely arranged into these series: Correspondence, Dissertation and Research, Morgan State University, Other Papers and AV Materials, Subject Files, and Writings. Beyond the topics discussed above, the materials also document grant proposals written by Cripps; his early dissertation work; coursework in a variety of settings; and his many publication projects.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged in the following series: Correspondence, Dissertation and Research, Films, Morgan State University, Other Papers and AV Materials, Still Photographs, Subject Files, and Writings. The Films and Still Photographs Series are open to use; the other series are closed pending processing.
Germany -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945; Stereotypes (social psychology) in mass media; Silent films -- United States; Race relations -- United States -- 20th century; Silent films; United States -- Social conditions -- 20th century; United States -- Ethnic relations -- 20th century; Black-and-white photographs; Motion pictures (visual works); Motion pictures -- United States -- History; African American artists; Race in motion pictures; Nazi propaganda -- Germany; African Americans in advertising; African Americans in mass media; African American soldiers; African Americans -- Civil rights; African Americans -- Pictorial works; Civil rights movements -- United States; African Americans in motion pictures; African Americans in the motion picture industry; Minorities in motion pictures; Videocassettes; Documentary films -- United States; Jews in motion pictures; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Cripps, Thomas; Micheaux, Oscar, 1884-1951
- Correspondence Series, 1971-2007 and undated [CLOSED], 8 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence is foldered by organization and topic and arranged alphabetically by folder title. Series includes correspondence regarding project ideas with major contemporary African American Studies figures such as Henry Louis Gates, Jr., John Blassingame, and Leon Litwack. "Fan Mail" folder contains international responses spanning from Sweden to Ghana to Nigeria. Original titles have been retained. Larger record storage containers are designated "RS."
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Series is closed pending processing.
  - General correspondence, 1974-2007 and undated (Box C1-C5)
  - Grant proposal information (Box C1-C5)
  - Correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box C6)
  - Conferences and foundations materials (Box C6)
  - Journal correspondence (Box C7 (RS))
  - Publishing and writings correspondence (Box C7 (RS))
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box C7 (RS))
  - Correspondence, 1978-1979, 1983, 1988-1989, and undated (Box C7 (RS))
  - Research/writing (Box C8 (RS))
  - Consulting projects (Box C8 (RS))
  - Glory- 54th, 1999 (Box C8 (RS))
- Dissertation and Research Series, circa 1960s [CLOSED], 17 boxes
  Records document Cripps's research leading to his dissertation on African Americans in film and popular culture. There are also related materials in Box P12. Original titles have been retained. Larger record storage containers are designated "RS."
  - Notecards for dissertation (Box DS1-DS5)
  - Research for dissertation (Box DS6-DS7)
  - Drafts of dissertation (Box DS8-DS9)
  - Research notecards - Movies, 1930s (Box DS10-DS11)
  - Research and methods (Box DS12 (RS))
  - Notecards for research (includes some MA notes) (Box DS13 (RS))
  - Notecards (Box DS14 (RS))
  - Archives and addresses (Box DS14 (RS))
  - Black film and music articles (Box DS14 (RS))
  - Research correspondence (Box DS14 (RS))
  - MA thesis and dissertation (Box DS14 (RS))
  - Research notecards (Box DS15 (RS))
  - Research notecards (Box DS16-DS17)
  - Dissertation notes (Box DS16-DS17)
- Films Series, circa 1898-1968, 40 reels or rolls
  Original films collected by Thomas Cripps; primarily black and white, silent, and 16mm. Early films, some from as early as 1898 and 1900, feature the cityscapes of New York, Baltimore, and San Francisco, and other urban centers. Some films portray African Americans in several wars, including the Spanish-American War, World War II, and the Korean War. Others document civil rights era events. Recorded political events include a Harry Truman speech concerning the Civil Rights Commission report, and a Lyndon Johnson speech on civil rights. Among the many notable actors and performers in the films are Duke Ellington, Jesse Owen, Louis Armstrong, Lincoln Perry ("Stepin Fetchit"), and Bert Williams. The entry for "Paisan - the Black Story" refers to Rossellini's film on the relations between Italians and American GIs during World War II, "Paisan," in which one episode centers on an African American GI and a Neapolitan street urchin. Arranged as received.
  [Original recordings are closed to use. Viewing copies are available for all films.]
  - Reel 1, 16 mm positive print, 100' (Box 1)
    North Star on Morgan State University News; man walking down street
    Existence and Location of Copies note
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 1]
  - Reel 2, 16 mm positive print, 75' (Box 1)
    March on Washington crowds, 1963
  - Reel 3, 16 mm positive print, 50' (Box 1)
    Black cavalry marching home from Spanish-American War
  - Reel 4, 16 mm positive print, 25' (Box 1)
    Madison Square, NYC, 1898
  - Reel 5, 16 mm negative, 150' (Box 1)
    Truman on Civil Rights Commission report and News in Brief (negative)
  - Reel 6, 16 mm positive print, 150' (Box 1)
    Los Angeles Riots, 1968; Selma March
  - Reel 7, 16 mm positive print, 600' (Box 1)
    Footage of various historically black colleges (Morgan Footage)
  - Reel 8, 16 mm positive print, 450' (Box 1)
    Baltimore fire of l904; vote against Daylight Savings; volunteer information for WWII
  - Reel 9, 16 mm positive print, 100' (Box 1)
    World War II footage with African American soldiers; Newsreel footage ­"Mrs. Roosevelt helps dedicate Negro Boys Club"; "Robot Cotton Picker"
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 2]
  - Reel 10, 16 mm positive print, 300' (Box 1)
    Street scenes ­1900s; black soldiers disembarking, Spanish-American War; Eisenhower/Kennedy/LBJ plead for race equality
  - Reel 11, 16 mm positive print, 350' (Box 1)
    Duke Ellington and his Symphony in Black
  - Reel 12, 16 mm positive print, 500' (Box 2)
    Uncle Tom's Cabin (Edison)
  - Reel 13, 16 mm positive print, 600' (Box 2)
    St. Louis Blues
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 3]
  - Reel 14, 16 mm positive print, 550' (Box 2)
    Jesse Owens Footage; Signal Corps; Unidentified speaker with several takes; Living conditions ­ Great Depression, l930s
  - Reel 15, 16 mm positive print, 150' (Box 2)
    Students at Booker T. Washington Institute; WWII: Tuskegee Airmen
  - Reel 16, 16 mm positive print, 600' (Box 2)
    Various Scenes from New York City: Military Procession; Arrival of Immigrants, Ellis Island; Panorama from the Times Building, NYC: Sorting Refuse at an incinerating plant, NYC; Union Iron Works; Harlem Street Scenes; Elevated Railroad, NYC; Bargain day, 14th St.; Dick Croker leaving Tammany Hall; Cardinal Gibbons.
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 4]
  - Reel 17, 16 mm positive print, 800' (Box 2)
    Ethnic Films:The Black Hand (Biograph); Romance of a Jewess (Or A Jewish Tragedy) (Biograph); The Heathen Chinese and the Sunday School Teacher (Biograph); Cohen's Fire Sale; Alfonse and Gaston Helping an Irishman
  - Reel 18, 16 mm positive print, 800' (Box 2)
    His Trust and His Trust Fulfilled
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 5]
  - Reel 19, 16 mm positive print, 900' (Box 2)
    "Soundies": Ellington, Fats Waller, Wingy Manone, Jimmy Rushing, Count Basie, Satchmo
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 5, 6]
  - Reel 20, 16 mm positive print, 1200' (Box 2)
    Sunday on the River
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 6]
  - Reel 21, 16 mm positive print, 700' (Box 3)
    Mr. Blabbermouth
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 7]
  - Reel 22, 16 mm positive print, 50' (Box 3)
    Misc. Seventies TV commercials
  - Reel 23, 16 mm positive print, 1300' (Box 3, Reel 23)
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 7, 8]
  - Reel 24, 16 mm positive print, 1400' (Box 3, Reel 24)
    The Negro Soldier
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 8, 9]
  - Reel 25, 16 mm positive print, 1700' (Box 3, Reel 25)
    Black Shadows on a Silver Screen
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 9, 10]
  - Reel 26, 8mm, length unknown (Box 3)
    A Natural Born Gambler
  - Reel 27, 16 mm positive print, 350' (Box 3)
    Spying the Spy (l9l9) - silent
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 10]
  - Reel 28, 16 mm positive print, 50' (Box 3)
    Thurgood Marshall joining the Supreme Court (newsreel); Selma - Montgomery March (Universal Newsreel); LBJ speech
  - Reel 29, 16 mm positive print, 200' (Box 3)
    Sidney Poiter accepts Oscar; Negro Youth Administration footage, l930s
  - Reel 30, 16 mm positive print, 150' (Box 3)
    LBJ greets troops; News in Brief ­ Social Security; Black troops, Korean War
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 10, 11]
  - Reel 31, 16 mm positive print, 300' (Box 3)
    City Scenes: New York City scenes, circa l900; Star theater; NY skyscrapers from North River; 1st Avenue - Seattle, Washington; San Francisco from balloon; Battery Park, NY; Cotton spinning
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 11]
  - Reel 32, 16 mm positive print, 400' (Box 3)
    Paisan - The Black Story
  - Reel 33, 16 mm positive print, 200' (Box 3)
    Watermelon Contest, Gator and the Picka-ninnie, A Bucket of Cream Ale, silent
  - Reel 34, 16 mm positive print, 350' (Box 3)
    Open the Door, Richard, with Lincoln Perry ("Stepin Fetchit")
  - Reel 35, 16 mm positive print, 250' (Box 3)
    Panorama, Union Square, San Francisco; Cardinal Gibbons; Cake Walk; Cavalry Troops; NY Street Scene; Gesture Fight on Hester Street (Part 1)
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 11, 12]
  - Reel 36, 16 mm positive print, 150' (Box 3)
    Panorama, Union Square, San Francisco; Cardinal Gibbons; Cake Walk; Cavalry Troops; NY Street Scene; Gesture Fight on Hester Street (Part 2)
  - Reel 37, 16 mm positive print, 300' (Box 3)
    The Fights of Nations, silent
    [VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 12]
  - Reel 38, 16 mm positive print, 350' (Box 3)
    Rhapsody in Black and Blue with Louis Armstrong (Satchmo), directed by Aubrey Scotto
  - Reel 39, 16 mm positive print, 500' (Box 3)
    Buck Dance, Broken Doll, silent
  - Reel 40, 16 mm positive print, 300' (Box 3)
    (unfinished) Spying the Spy,
- Morgan State University Series, 1974-1995 and undated [CLOSED], 20 boxes
  An extensive set of files related to television programming, publicity, and teaching material generated from Cripps's position at Morgan State. Series includes lesson plans, notes, and list of accompanying images for a variety of class topics based on African American history such as Blacks and the Presidency, From Colonization to Nationalism, Latin American Comparisons, and Jazz Tradition. Some files cover a short film script Cripps wrote for Anacostia Museum concerning 1920s Black Renaissance and film, Maryland Committee for the Humanities materials, and course exams and notes for The Social History of American Broadcasting course at MSU. All relevant information is listed in folders marked "Group W, referring to the television news company, Westinghouse, which refers to their series of television networks in major cities as "Group W."
  A large component of the series relates to a television program Cripps hosted in the 1970s, The 'Negro' In United States History, an educational series for the general public created through the collaboration of several instructors. It was broadcast Saturday and Sunday mornings. The in-class lecture ran every Saturday from 11:00am-1:00pm for those registered. Cripps offered the syllabus for free upon request for interested, unregistered viewers. The audience who wrote in came from many segments of the community, included the incarcerated. The primary text for this book was John Hope Franklin's From Slavery to Freedom.
  Included in the "Fan Mail" folder is a 1975 letter from Roosevelt Drummond. Drummond was convicted on charges stemming from robbery and drug dealing during his youth. In prison, he became a member of the Black Guerilla Family (BGF), a national gang founded by Soledad Brother George Jackson. During his time in prison, Drummond made a number of escape attempts, which he references in the letter to Cripps. In 2009, he was indicted alongside other BGF members and prison officials for drug conspiracy. Drummond made a final escape just prior to the indictment and has been a federal fugitive since.
  Original titles have been retained. Boxes designated "RS" are larger record storage cartons.
  - American Cinema telecourse (Box MSU 1)
  - Photo stills (Box MSU 1)
  - Baltimore TV (Box MSU 1)
  - North Star (Box MSU 2)
  - NEH Black Baltimore proposal (Box MSU 2)
  - Programs and proposals, 1974-1975 (Box MSU 3)
  - Black Baltimore (Box MSU 4)
  - Group W. (Box MSU 5)
  - Proposals (Box MSU 5)
  - Group W. (Box MSU 6)
  - History of Broadcasting course (Box MSU 6)
  - Budget (Box MSU 7)
  - Memos (Box MSU 7)
  - Mail (Box MSU 7)
  - Publicity (Box MSU 8)
  - Permissions (Box MSU 8)
  - Scripts (Box MSU 8)
  - "Negro in the U.S." (Box MSU 8)
  - Anacostia Museum (Box MSU 9)
  - Maryland Commission for Humanities (Box MSU 9)
  - Public broadcasting (Box MSU 9)
  - Programs on African Americans (TV) (Box MSU 10-MSU 11)
    These last two boxes included this description by Cripps: "This box constitutes a Morgan movement toward affecting TV racially at its source - the studio and the booth. Professors Dates (now Dean of the [?] School at Howard) and Cripps (now Distinguished Professor Emeritus) together and separately developed, hosted, wrote, consulted on almost 2 decades of TV in concert with Post-Newsweek, WJZ, WBAL, many other projects or consultants - this at a crucial moment from 1963-1976."
  - History dept., etc. (Box MSU 12)
  - Teaching correspondence (including re: grades) (Box MSU 12)
  - Dept. business (Box MSU 13)
  - Graduate committee (Box MSU 13)
  - Faculty recruitment (Box MSU 13)
  - Ph.D. Program, 1977-1991 (Box MSU 14)
  - History Dept. restructuring (Box MSU 14)
  - Teacher evaluations (Box MSU 15)
  - Salary (Box MSU 15)
  - Social studies evaluations (Box MSU 15)
  - Programming (TV) (Box MSU 16)
  - Lawsuit against Cripps and others, re: public broadcasting, 1974-1975 (Box MSU 17)
  - Course development (including Harvard) (Box MSU 18 (RS))
  - Conferences (Box MSU 18 (RS))
  - Professional organizations (fellowships, awards) (Box MSU 18 (RS))
  - TV (Box MSU 19 (RS))
  - Career experiences - trips, nominations, reference requests (Box MSU 19 (RS))
  - Correspondence (Box MSU 19 (RS))
  - Publicity (Box MSU 19 (RS))
  - Teaching materials (Box MSU 19 (RS))
  - Publicity (Box MSU 20 (RS))
  - Fellowships (Box MSU 20 (RS))
  - Teaching appointments (Box MSU 20 (RS))
  - Contracts (Box MSU 20 (RS))
  - Broadcasting (Box MSU 20 (RS))
  - Employee materials (Box MSU 20 (RS))
- Other Papers and Audiovisual Materials Series, 1966-1993 [CLOSED], 12 boxes
  Contains an assortment of uncategorized working files, chiefly concerning grant proposals, teaching positions, Cripps's own coursework as a student, and a series of audiovisual recordings. Larger record storage cartons are designated "RS."
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Pedagogical files (Box P1-P4)
    Cripps's schoolwork, and courses taught by Cripps at MSU.
  - Clippings (some grant proposals) (Box P4-P6)
  - Grant proposals (Box P7-P9)
    Foldered by proposal and labeled with the name of the funding source and the project for which funding was solicited.
  - Johns Hopkins University (Box P10 (RS))
  - CD Project (Box P10 (RS))
  - Harvard visiting appointment (Box P10 (RS))
  - Audiocassette tapes and slides (Box P11 (RS))
  - Notecards (belongs with DS series) (Box P12 (RS))
  - VHS cassette recording (Box P12 (RS))
  - Reel-to-reel recordings (Box P12 (RS))
  - VHS cassette recordings, 1918-1984; 9 VHS (Box P13)
- Still Photographs Series, 1839-1989, 8 boxes
  Consists of hundreds of black and white publicity stills and other images collected by Thomas Cripps over many years, taken from films featuring African American actors or African American producers and directors from the silent film era through the 1970s. Almost all derive from American-made films, but there is also a large group of stills originating from British films. One significant group contains images from pioneer African American director Oscar Micheaux's movies. Titles refer either to individual films, or to broad subjects.
  To improve housing, contents of original envelopes have been refoldered, but Cripps's content lists which provide fuller descriptive access to individual images have been photocopied and placed in each folder with its corresponding group of stills. A few folders include other film publicity or correspondence. Arranged as received, in alphabetical order by film title or topical heading. Original folder titles retained. Dates added by staff are in brackets.
  - Folders Arranged by Film Title, 1904-198 and undated4
    - The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, 1960 (Box ST1)
    - All About Eve, 1950 (Box ST1)
    - Battle of Algiers, 1968 (Box ST1)
    - Birth of a Nation, 1915 (Box ST1)
    - Black Like Me, [1964] (Box ST1)
    - Born to Sing, 1942 (Box ST1)
    - The Breaking Point, 1950; To Have, to Have Not, [1944] (Box ST1)
    - Bright Road, 1953 (Box ST1)
    - A Bucket of Cream Ale, 1904 (Box ST1)
    - Burning Cross, [1947] (Box ST1)
    - Cabin in the Sky, 1943, 2 folders (Box ST1)
    - The Cardinal, 1963 (Box ST1)
    - Carib Gold, [1957] (Box ST1)
    - Carmen Jones, 1955 (Box ST1)
    - Casablanca, [1942] (Box ST1)
    - Ciné Club Nine, undated (Box ST1)
    - The Color Purple, [1985] (Box ST1)
    - The Cool World, 1964 (Box ST1)
    - The Cosby Show, 1984 (Box ST1)
    - Defiant Ones, 1958 (Box ST1)
    - Demetrius and the Gladiators, [1954] (Box ST1)
    - Detective Story, [1951] (Box ST1)
    - Dutchman, 1967 (Box ST1)
    - Edge of the City, [1957] (Box ST1)
    - Emperor Jones, 1933 (Box ST1)
    - Glory Alley, 1947 (Box ST1)
    - The Gorgeous Hussy, 1936 (Box ST1)
    - The Great White Hope, 1969 (Box ST1)
    - Green Pastures, [1936] (Box ST1)
    - Guess Who's Coming to Dinner?, 1967 (Box ST1)
    - Hallelujah!, 1929 (Box ST1)
    - Hallelujah-Hearts in Dixie, [1929] (Box ST1)
    - Hearts and Flags, 1911 (Box ST1)
    - His Trust and His Trust Fulfilled, 1911 (Box ST1)